let's do some structure stuff okay you
were thinking that I'll go home early
but when's the last time that happened
when Galya let's do some structure stuff
but I will still try to finish early
okay just try and no promise we were
supposed to be talking about the
foundation 18 courses we're trying to do
a couple of things we're trying to
identify which topic in which school and
what's the famous book that's used and
then of course we want to know the topic
and the last thing we want to know the
floor why did it come from the last one
and why is it going into the next one
geshe-la
told you the secret secret teaching like
I don't know somebody did a bad
translation of what to call Tibetan Book
of the Dead or something like that you
see like my Lama was sick and I had
extra time so I did the diamond cutter
see but you're not gonna say that okay
you're gonna say logically emptiness
teaching should come course six gears
lost said okay there's open teaching
there's secret teaching okay course
thirteen I lost half my students because
it was so hard so I did course fourteen
is how to have a like touchy is the
touchy-feely course they all came back
by the way so that's the flow but don't
tell anybody will say Buddhist logic is
necessary and compassion is necessary
okay so what course Murray on don't
remember
we finished Bodhisattva vows we finished
eight we finished death and well then
what's nine oh yeah another popular
class
you're a bad person stop doing it yeah
so I met the highest Lama in the world
by the way and they asked me I get
offered them two courses in person and
then they said well how did you handle
vinaya because I'm not supposed to teach
monk vows to people who don't have monk
stuff so they said oh there must have
been a short course because you can only
do the one-day vows in their lifetime
vows and I said well I used some copper
okay which is a famous summary of the
vows without mentioning the vows okay so
I'm still legal okay if you want to know
the vows 253 monks Fels 364 nuns vows
the nuns vows in Tibet have been lost
for I don't know a thousand years or
eight hundred years okay some King evil
king killed all the nuns and there
weren't enough survivors to hold the
ceremony to make a new nun so there has
to be more than I think there has to be
2120 there has to be a certain number of
nuns there and he killed so many that
there wasn't enough nuns to make a new
full nun so for the last I don't know
eight hundred years I'm guessing you
couldn't take full nuns vows in Tibet
and guess who revived them Diamond
Mountain okay we did it here we we found
this three hundred sixty four votes and
we worked hard on them and we found the
ancient ceremonies for making nuns and
we recovered them John Brady and we've
translated them and we made full nuns
here and it was very controversial we
got criticized by big people and now
they're doing it themselves he
okay so anyway I want to brag about
course number nine and it's an amazing
summary of the Vinaya Sutra written by
Tom copper okay and now that book is so
short that you need an explanation okay
and I I decided to use one by se llama
Quicksilver okay his name is mucho mucho
Quicksilver silver water
mucho Quicksilver mercury which is used
in Tonto by the way in the ancient times
don't use it it's a poison don't try it
okay but his name is llama Quicksilver
and he's amazing llama from about 300
years ago and he's famous for very good
commentaries so we used his explanation
of takapa summary of the eight kinds of
protein moksha vows a party moksha for
10 cents
what's it mean yeah okay hustle ten five
cents each okay hustle gets five cents
work is fastened finally what they're
worth just kidding don't get eight
worldly thoughts about it okay
yeah the subject of vinaya is patty
machiavel which means the vows you have
to keep to reach nirvana okay not
Buddhahood but to stop your suffering
personally the vows of monks nuns
lifetime laymen vow one-day vows which
Alison also did a great job translating
and Stanley okay and you can ask them
for the translation someday they did the
Mahayana one day vow which is not in
this course
I say again yeah we translated it and we
did it in Thailand so if you want a copy
talk to them there's a one-day value can
take with fasting you can fast for the
day and it's a very sweet vow it's a
one-day Mahayana vow but there is a
one-day vow Hinayana vow which we will
study in this course and they're very
similar most of it is similar okay now
so we have the commentary by Quicksilver
listen going backwards
Genki Michael ken Rinpoche cheetah
remember to Pabon krimpet a poem says
Lama
you can go back like that you will hit
Lama Quicksilver I'm talking tantric
lineage okay I'm talking diamond way
lineage quicksilver's explanation of how
to meet the a Ginga you two more angel
of diamond how to find her how to meet
her and how to become her student which
is one of the biggest subjects of Tantra
he wrote the best books he wrote two of
the best
okay so he's I if you ask about flow
what's the answer - Allah was setting
you up for Tantra in the lowest school
okay and the lesson there is why why are
we have a book by Lama quicksilver about
the lowest school what's the flow answer
he wrote a lot of the books you're going
to study in Tantra course I translated
the whole book okay you're gonna get the
whole Lama quicksilver's [__] on you
Jim oh okay so that's part of the flow
part of the flow of DCI foundation
course number nine is to set you up for
Tantra before you know okay people say
all gays lots not very interesting yeah
but you cannot enter Tantra without it
okay okay without a good ethical life
you will fail if you try to do Tantra
okay it's the foundation of Tantra
treating other people kindly treating
other people respectfully is the basis
of secret practice okay and if you don't
know denial you can't touch Tantra okay
there's a direct connection okay why you
want to see angels come to you and teach
you in person you better have some good
seeds how do you make good seeds you be
nice to other people well how do I make
those seeds there's a book called Vinaya
Sutra it tells you the coolest seeds to
make
okay got it no killing no stealing no
stealing other people's wives etc etc
okay it doesn't sound very sexy but it's
the ultimate sexy okay keep your keep
your vows treat other people nice treat
other people as you would like to be
treated your stuff okay good
yeah so the main book is called the
essence of the ocean do a gutter nimble
and the commentaries by master Dharma
Bhadra Master Quicksilver by the way I
think I ask you this question already in
this course towards the end I threw in
another letter but some copper to his
disciple that he banished is too bad to
make 108 monasteries okay there's a
second letter in the 18 courses and it
comes in course 9 there's a second
letter that tsongkhapa wrote to him and
it's a response to a letter that he got
from know and Appa who said I not only
build these monasteries but I I created
a bunch of monks and nuns I made the
first monks and nuns in the east part of
Tibetan he's bragging to his teacher and
some copper wrote him back a long letter
which I translated and put into this
course why yeah in the letter some
copper draws the connection between
vinaya and successful meditation okay
because people always ask me geshe-la do
we put the left foot up first or do we
put the right foot up first
you know do we use a soft cushion or a
hard cushion do we put the left hand
down first or the right hand you know do
we connect the thumb so we don't do a
chin mudra or we hold it up or we hold
it down people always asking me stuff
like this and as an AC I teacher give
them a serious censor Oh always hold the
mom always left foot first
then right foot always left hand down
first right hand down first
many prana reasons you have to do that
then when they get to course 9 tell them
it doesn't matter at all okay what makes
good meditation it's not how you sit how
you treat other people and that was some
coppice greatest contribution to the
practice of meditation in his life okay
and he wrote thousands of pages about
meditation but that little letter that
he wrote to his beloved disciple that he
kicked out to go do organizing work
right jasmine in other countries like
bali or thailand you know he loved the
students so much that he gave the
student the most important job and and
they had a beautiful relationship okay
and then he wrote the letter and he said
listen i'm so happy you made some monks
and i'm so happy they are learning two
old old monks rules because they will
have good meditation he didn't say there
will be nice people or everyone will
like them he said though only those
people will have good meditation because
what you hear in your mind as you try to
meditate is coming out of the stage you
planted last week okay if your mind
keeps talking about lunch it's because
you bothered someone else's
concentration last week your husband was
trying to focus on something for work
and you came in and honey you know wait
I want to tell you about what's going on
you know and so interrupting people
bothering other people is a special
cause to have your own mind talking
about lunch during meditation
okay so respect other people's peace of
mind okay by the way
respecting other people's concentration
okay they're focusing on a project
they're learning some music they're
enjoying some music you know not bother
checking people before you talk to them
okay checking if it's a good time for
them it's a very important skill for a
meditator because those are the seeds
you need to meditate okay if you respect
other people's peace of mind and you
don't irritate them you don't bother
them if you have to tell them bad news
pick the time morning is good time and
never criticize someone in the evening
okay if you gotta tell your student bad
news tell them in the morning okay
because the otherwise they won't sleep
and they'll they'll be a wreck the next
day and the next thing okay
get people bad news in the morning okay
give them good news in the evening okay
general 66 rule for you okay if you have
to criticize your student do it in the
morning okay that gives them time to
recover okay all right respect other
people's peace of mind the ten good
deeds is a good list of respect the good
the ten good days list is a great way to
have good meditation and that's an
important teaching but tsongkhapa that
he wrote to his disciple and we added it
to this course cool okay I had something
else to say about that what was done
yeah anyway that's enough
yeah if you want your mind to be quiet
that seeds opening in your mind at 65
per second of silence silence seeds are
opening 65 per second in your mind and
that's what you call good meditation
okay you got a string of good seeds
going off 65 per second
silence seeds balance seeds
satisfactions contentment seeds all
these beautiful meditations focuses you
have to plan them okay you have to plant
them on purpose
don't expect to have watermelons if you
didn't plant them it rarely happens okay
plant your meditation for next week this
week by not bothering other people I
know what I wanted to add say she sick
no sorry say it's part of the word say
she okay mr. know-it-all say she say
number she come on who's got that huh
she is the same for right sir sir
same I think it came from the same route
same is food a sustenance yeah four
kinds of sustenance for things you need
to eat every day or two or you will get
sick or you won't live okay
first one is easy come kiss a yeah
physical food okay
physical food second one is sleep okay
you want to have fun with an employee in
your company take the nicest person in
the company and don't let them sleep for
three four days and they become the
meanest person in the company it's kind
of amazing
I mean sometimes do it just for fun
okay lack of sleep makes anybody it
doesn't matter how good person you are
if you don't stay for three or four days
you will be terrible you'll be a
terrible person I'm sorry okay
second kind of food third kind of food
hope okay hope and what's the famous
example yeah a horse in the I don't know
Syrian desert who's dying of thirst okay
and then they see an oasis they will no
horse ever died two meters from the
water it's it never happened in history
okay what keeps them going the last two
meters hope okay they can see the water
no horse ever died two meters from the
water okay hope can sustain a human body
and Brutus don't eat okay they have the
fourth kind of food focus focus
they don't have to eat by the way if
your meditation gets really good you
will have this experience I predict okay
you get prediction today you'll be
sitting in a quiet place like a library
and you will notice that you didn't
breathe for ten minutes and you feel
fine you feel normal
okay you'll say oh my god I didn't
breathe for ten minutes
why breath is food that is kumki say
okay you don't need it to survive you
need to focus okay if your focus is
strong enough you don't need to eat okay
and you don't need breath okay it's very
interesting
then I'll tell you a funny thing about
yoga
I had a yoga teacher they said hold your
breath for as long as you can
and I'm like why and they said you're
gonna reach what is it kombucha what it
has another name Kerala kombucha
the the the the spontaneous stopping of
your breath it has a name in yoga kevala
khumba kar komak up means a vase a
Chinese vase with the top here and the
kevala means automatic you didn't try to
do it it just happened spontaneous so
Kevlar kombucha means your breath stop
so there's all these yoga schools they
say hold your breath for you know five
minutes then hold your breath for ten
minutes and there you know and everyone
in the room is like and maybe you'll get
up to ten minutes or something running
on three minutes four minutes and you
get a headache you get known for three
years
really that's not how you stop your
breath okay focus perfect your
meditation and it will stop on its own
and you will notice it one day I didn't
breathe for ten minutes okay
it's not there is pranayama right in in
Tantra and you will learn it and there's
many venomous luminal go to is the most
famous but holding your breath is not
going to stop you from breathing got it
learn to meditate deeply and you don't
have to breathe anymore okay you got the
food the other way why are we talking
about that a human being needs focus as
much as they need food okay if you
deprive a human being a sleep for three
four days I did it just for fun the
nicest person in your company will
become the biggest I almost said [__]
but I'm not allowed to say that my
teacher hates it when I curse by the way
so don't let me curse in a class anyway
if you don't let people focus
they will also go crazy okay so a good
way to ruin a good employee is to keep
interrupting them every half hour with a
different job okay okay just teaching
you
future diamond Academy if you want to
lose a good employee like Annie keep
interrupting them and giving them
another jump and it will make them crazy
and that's why because focus is a kind
of food focus is a kind of fun okay why
are we talking about this yeah we're
talking about how to plant the seeds for
good meditation don't interrupt
other people's focus you know come back
when they're not busy and tell them
about the what the cat did okay don't
interrupt people when you don't
absolutely have to if you have to do it
you know hey the house is on fire honey
maybe we need to do something that's
okay that's not a bad seat for
meditation but in general be respectful
of other people's focus if your
husband's reading a book if someone's
listening to music wait till they're
finished okay and then talk to them
about the bills okay okay got it
and your meditation will improve because
that's the only reason for meditation
that's the only cause of good meditation
there's no other consonant it doesn't
matter how you say it doesn't matter
what [__] leg you put on first okay the
best meditator in my gosh e-class
meditated on his back
and one night he beat the abbot of
touching limbo in a debate in front of
like a thousand people this is the guy
who only study on his back illegally and
he had the illegal tape recorder with
rock and roll okay but he never
interrupted other people and his focus
was garden it's not the posture it's how
much C's do you have okay
that's the connection between class
number nine and class number three good
question yeah absolutely yeah
during the book help cemented because
when you do bother other people you
can't confess and clean the scene okay
let's try that I mean I didn't think
about it to be honest but how does nine
connect to egg huh
eight it's like death meditation nine is
might be a good person any connection
there yeah not to go to the hell realms
how's that okay I so I guess there's
some flow there how about nine and ten
what's ten yeah so look I have 11
minutes I'll start and I won't finish
okay probably the most important book
for Bodhisattvas is guess what it's
called a guide to the Bodhisattvas way
of life okay so it's written by shanti
demo around master shanti they were
around 700 AD okay around tongue channel
right Tong dynasty early 10th dynasty no
it's right in the middle in the middle
of Tang Dynasty yeah tight song maybe I
think so anyway so he wrote a book
called bloody stuff guide to the boys
office way of life okay I'm gonna tell
you part is 39 I'll tell you part is 30
tomorrow okay it's a kid story he would
say boo so cool yeah he had a nickname
in the monastery called boo so cool
boo circle means mr. lazy mister do
nothing and so he had a reputation in
the monastery he didn't study well he
wasn't a good teacher
he didn't show up in the kitchen to help
with the dishes he didn't help roll the
carpets up before yoga and he especially
didn't help roll them back after younger
basically he seemed to be the laziest
monk in the monastery okay and the
Munster I got tired of feeding him you
know we're feeding this guy every day
and he just doesn't do anything you know
so they set a meeting they said let's
kick this guy on and there was a very
wise abbot who was a fool and he said
let's let's help him kick himself out
you know then we don't have any
responsibility so so he said what's your
plan
he said let's ask him to teach teach a
class you know and he'll make a fool out
of himself and then we can tell him you
know we need people who know how to
teach in the monastery we don't we can't
feed you anymore you have to leave okay
so they went to him and they told him
you have to teach okay and so he said
you want me to teach something somebody
else wrote you want me to something I
wrote and they're like hahaha yeah yeah
yeah did your thing okay yeah you can't
even write you know he said okay I'll
teach something and then he sat down and
he taught the bloody trial of a time he
taught the guide to the Bodhisattvas way
of life which is basically a review of
the ten Bodhisattva levels and the six
perfections okay basically although
importantly it includes the meditation
preliminaries okay so the first part
that we study in ACI is the same
preliminaries I taught you from his book
okay so he taught and it it's probably I
think surely it's the greatest
Bodhisattva book ever written ever in
Buddhism even even more cool than what
Buddha said I'm sorry
like unbelievable
sweet book and full of incredibly funny
fun deep the emptiness section is
studied by or gaseous you know it's it's
the best emptiness section ever written
okay and it's written in the in the as
personal advice how to be a bodhisattva
okay so it's not part of the Geisha
course all right it's very interesting
oh by the way you won't know the end of
the story in the middle of the wisdom
chapter he started to rise off the seat
into the sky and I put a picture of it
in your reading and the caption if you
can read Tibetan maybe a word will
translate it for you I found it in
there's the normal picture go down to
the next picture
maybe the course eleven can you just
scroll down
that's Celtic J who wrote a great
commentary okay next there you go
what's it what's the last three
syllables their word was so cool okay
this is Baku this is him flying off okay
he's got his book in his hand you know
and he's flying off and when he got deep
into emptiness he started to rise up in
the air okay and then there were some
monks in the audience who were high
Yogi's and they followed him they also
said hey I want to hear the end and they
started going up in this guy with him so
there's a circle of people around Santi
there he's like going up higher higher
and then people dropped out you know
people can't go so high they can't
follow him you know and it got less and
less and less and it finally they give
up and he's still teaching in the sky
and he
South India you know and he disappeared
and he never came back and it's a famous
story then they had a big meeting and
they oh my god this is the best place on
for him and his aunt and his teaching is
the best emptyness teaching we ever
heard we need to get the rest
so they actually sent search parties to
many cities they asking did did a guide
land here with a book in his hand you
know and they found him and they said
you know we apologize we made a big
mistake you actually a great master
please come back to the monastery and he
said go to hell
I'm sorry he said I neglect decline
respectfully and he never went back and
which is another thing about criticism
right there were all good monks they're
all nice monks but they made a big
mistake
you know then they send another team
like later and they said late we
understand you don't want to come back
we can't blame you but Kelly had the
book and he said I knew you're gonna ask
me that so I made a copy and I hid it in
the roof of my monks room in the up
above the wood you can find it there
I left your copy you know and so there's
a copy ok so the next three courses
because that is so important that book
is so important for how to be a
bodhisattva
i I did three courses it's 20% of the
ACI foundation courses because the last
three courses are review so three of the
15 courses are shunted in one guide to
the Bodhisattvas way of life ten eleven
and twelve am i right okay so I'm gonna
do two things tomorrow
I'll tell you the subjects that how I
split it up and why I split it up okay
why I split it up that way okay and then
I'm gonna let you out two minutes early
[Music]
good night I knew you'd be happy you
guys think - oh let's see
by the way sure a McDonald McDaniel I'm
sorry is the registrar of a CI for like
the last 20 years in front and so
without pay by the way she's the
financial officer of a large city in in
the United States so she's doing it for
free which is amazing so we have one of
the most talented managers of a city in
the room and for free she's keeping all
your records for the last I don't know I
think it's about 15 20 years although
she's only 30
so you should a you should thank her be
you should get on her good side and
maybe your grades will improve okay
would you like to do my no and we'd like
to thank you for you
[Applause]
purchasing meth or tongue republishing
and a camp adding some cash and maintain
the liking don't come down
she nodded sharp he's on guard outside
now man down yeah yeah
they come son Amish a total shin turn
our mission a to number Connie top by
the way she raised father dr. Michael
Moore is a started as a heart surgeon
and later became a very famous
anesthesiologist anesthesiologist and I
think about 20 years ago or longer
towards the beginning of ACI
he offered to check homeworks for ACI
students in prisons and it became
extremely popular because they're not
allowed to have there's a like you can't
send them cd-roms because they can make
knives out of them stuff like that so he
took care of them for about 20-25 years
and he's still doing it and I think we
should give him a head yeah
[Music]
[Applause]
they love to write long answers because
they don't have anything else to do and
it you have to have so much patience to
check their homework because they add 17
pages to the homework and because
they're lonely and they and they have a
lot of time okay